<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2404 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2404.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2405 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2405.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2410 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2410.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2451 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2451.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3566 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3566.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3602 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3602.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3686 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3686.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4106 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4106.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4301 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4301.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4302 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4302.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4303 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4303.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4309 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4309.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4543 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4543.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4835 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4835.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7321 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7321.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7634 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7634.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-mglt-ipsecme-rfc7321bis-01"
	obsoletes="7321"
	ipr="trust200902">
<front>

<title abbrev="ESP and AH Algorithm Requirements">Cryptographic
Algorithm Implementation Requirements and Usage Guidance for Encapsulating
Security Payload (ESP) and Authentication Header (AH)</title>

   <author fullname="Daniel Migault" initials="D." surname="Migault">
      <organization> Ericsson </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street> 8400 boulevard Decarie </street>
          <city> Montreal, QC </city>
          <code> H4P 2N2 </code>
          <country> Canada </country>
        </postal>
        <phone> +1 514-452-2160 </phone>
        <email> daniel.migault@ericsson.com </email>
      </address>
    </author>

<author initials='J.M' surname="Mattsson" fullname='John Mattsson'>
    <organization abbrev="Ericsson">Ericsson AB</organization>
    <address>
        <postal>
            <street>SE-164 80 Stockholm</street>
            <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
        <email>john.mattsson@ericsson.com</email>
    </address>
</author>

    <author fullname="Paul Wouters" initials="P." surname="Wouters">
      <organization>Red Hat</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
              <street/>
              <city/>
              <region/>
              <code/>
              <country/>
        </postal>
        <email>pwouters@redhat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="Y." surname="Nir" fullname="Yoav Nir">
      <organization abbrev="Check Point">Check Point Software Technologies Ltd.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5 Hasolelim st.</street>
          <city>Tel Aviv</city>
          <code>6789735</code>
          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ynir.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='T.' surname='Kivinen' fullname='Tero Kivinen'>
      <organization>INSIDE Secure</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Eerikinkatu 28</street>
          <code>FI-00180</code>
          <city>HELSINKI</city>
          <country>FI</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kivinen@iki.fi</email>
      </address>
    </author>


<date/>

<abstract>

<t>This document updates the Cryptographic Algorithm Implementation Requirements for ESP
and AH. The goal of these document is to enable ESP and AH to benefit from cryptography 
that is up to date while making IPsec interoperable.</t>

<t>This document obsoletes RFC 7321 on the cryptographic recommendations only.</t>

</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t>The Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) <xref target="RFC4303"/> and
the Authentication Header (AH) <xref target="RFC4302"/> are the
mechanisms for applying cryptographic protection to data being sent over
an IPsec Security Association (SA) <xref target="RFC4301"/>.</t>



<t>This document provides guidance and recommendations so that ESP and
    AH can be used with a cryptographic algorithms that are up to date.
	The challenge of such document is to make sure that over the time 
	IPsec implementations can use secure and up-to-date cryptographic
	algorithms while keeping IPsec interoperable.</t>


     <section title="Updating Algorithm Implementation Requirements and Usage Guidance">
      <t> The field of cryptography evolves continuously. New stronger
      algorithms appear and existing algorithms are found to be less
      secure then originally thought. Therefore, algorithm
      implementation requirements and usage guidance need to be
      updated from time to time to reflect the new reality. The
      choices for algorithms must be conservative to minimize the risk
      of algorithm compromise. Algorithms need to be suitable for a
      wide variety of CPU architectures and device deployments ranging
      from high end bulk encryption devices to small low-power IoT
      devices.</t>

      <t> The algorithm implementation requirements and usage guidance
      may need to change over time to adapt to the changing world. For
      this reason, the selection of mandatory-to-implement algorithms
      was removed from the main IKEv2 specification and placed in a
      separate document. </t>

     </section>


     <section title="Updating Algorithm Requirement Levels">
      <t>The mandatory-to-implement algorithm of tomorrow should
      already be available in most implementations of AH/ESP by the time
      it is made mandatory. This document attempts to identify and
      introduce those algorithms for future mandatory-to-implement
      status. There is no guarantee that the algorithms in use today
      may become mandatory in the future. Published algorithms are
      continuously subjected to cryptographic attack and may become
      too weak or could become completely broken before this document
      is updated.</t>

      <t> This document only provides recommendations for the
      mandatory-to-implement algorithms or algorithms too weak that
      are recommended not to be implemented. As a result, any
      algorithm listed at the IPsec IANA registry not mentioned in
      this document MAY be implemented. As <xref target="RFC7321"/> 
      omitted most of the algorithms mentioned by the IPsec IANA 
      repository, which makes it difficult to define whether non 
      mentioned algorithms are optional to implement or must not
      be implemented as they are too weak. This document provides 
      explicit guidance for all
      of them. It is expected that this document will be updated 
      over time and next versions will only mention algorithms which
      status has evolved. For clarification when an algorithm has been
      mentioned in <xref target="RFC7321"/>, this document states 
      explicitly the update of the status.</t> 
	  
	  <!--
	  For clarification and
      consistency with <xref target="RFC7321"/> an algorithm will be
      denoted here as MAY only when it has been downgraded.</t>
      -->
	  
      <t> Although this document updates the algorithms to keep the
      AH/ESP communication secure over time, it also aims at providing
      recommendations so that AH/ESP implementations remain
      interoperable. AH/ESP interoperability is addressed by an
      incremental introduction or deprecation of algorithms. In
      addition, this document also considers the new use cases for
      AH/ESP deployment, such as Internet of Things (IoT).</t>

      <t> It is expected that deprecation of an algorithm is performed
      gradually. This provides time for various implementations to
      update their implemented algorithms while remaining
      interoperable. Unless there are strong security reasons, an
      algorithm is expected to be downgraded from MUST to MUST- or
      SHOULD, instead of MUST NOT. Similarly, an algorithm that has
      not been mentioned as mandatory-to-implement is expected to be
      introduced with a SHOULD instead of a MUST.</t>

      <t>The current trend toward Internet of Things and its adoption
      of AH/ESP requires this specific use case to be taken into
      account as well. IoT devices are resource constrained devices
      and their choice of algorithms are motivated by minimizing the
      footprint of the code, the computation effort and the size of
      the messages to send. This document indicates "[IoT]" when a
      specified algorithm is specifically listed for IoT devices.
      Requirement levels that are marked as "IoT" apply to IoT devices
      and to server-side implementations that might presumably need to
      interoperate with them, including any general-purpose VPN
      gateways.</t>
      
     </section>

     <section title="Document Audience">
      <t>The recommendations of this document mostly target AH/ESP
      implementers as implementations need to meet both high security
      expectations as well as high interoperability between various
      vendors and with different versions. Interoperability requires a
      smooth move to more secure cipher suites. This may differ from a
      user point of view that may deploy and configure AH/ESP with only
      the safest cipher suite.</t>

      <t>This document does not give any recommendations for the use
      of algorithms, it only gives implementation recommendations for
      implementations. The use of algorithms by users is dictated by
      the security policy requirements for that specific user, and are
      outside the scope of this document.</t>

      <t> The algorithms considered here are listed by the IANA as part 
	  of the IKEv2 parameters. IKEv1 is out of scope of this document.
       IKEv1 is deprecated
      and the recommendations of this document must not be considered
      for IKEv1, nor IKEv1 parameters be considered by this document.</t>
     </section>

</section> 

<section title="Requirements Language">

<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

<t>Following <xref target="RFC4835"/>, we define some additional key
words:</t>

<t><list style="hanging">

<t hangText="MUST-"> This term means the same as MUST. However, we
expect that at some point in the future this algorithm will no
longer be a MUST.</t>

<t hangText="SHOULD+"> This term means the same as SHOULD.
However, it is likely that an algorithm marked as SHOULD+ will be
promoted at some future time to be a MUST.</t>

</list></t>

</section>


<section title="ESP Encryption Algorithms" anchor="sec-encr">

        <texttable anchor="tbl_enc" suppress-title="true">
          <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Status</ttcol>
          <ttcol>AEAD</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Comment</ttcol>
<c>ENCR_DES_IV64     </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT   </c><c> No     </c><c> UNSPECIFIED </c>
<c>ENCR_DES          </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT   </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC2405]   </c>
<c>ENCR_3DES         </c><c> SHOULD&nbsp;NOT </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC2451]   </c>
<c>ENCR_RC5          </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT   </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC2451]   </c>
<c>ENCR_IDEA         </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT   </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC2451]   </c>
<c>ENCR_CAST         </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT   </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC2451]   </c>
<c>ENCR_BLOWFISH     </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT   </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC2451]   </c>
<c>ENCR_3IDEA        </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT   </c><c> No     </c><c> UNSPECIFIED </c>
<c>ENCR_DES_IV32     </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT   </c><c> No     </c><c> UNSPECIFIED </c>
<c>ENCR_NULL         </c><c> MUST       </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC2410]   </c>
<c>ENCR_AES_CBC      </c><c> MUST       </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC3602][1] </c>
<c>ENCR_AES_CTR      </c><c> MAY        </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC3686]   </c>
<c>ENCR_AES_CCM_8    </c><c> SHOULD     </c><c> Yes    </c><c> [RFC4309][1][IoT] </c>
<c>ENCR_AES_CCM_12   </c><c> MAY        </c><c> Yes    </c><c> [RFC4309]   </c>
<c>ENCR_AES_CCM_16   </c><c> SHOULD     </c><c> Yes    </c><c> [RFC4309][1]</c>
<c>AES-GCM_8         </c><c> MAY       </c><c> Yes    </c><c> [RFC4106] </c>
<c>AES-GCM_12        </c><c> MAY      </c><c> Yes    </c><c> [RFC4106] </c>
<c>AES-GCM_16        </c><c> MUST     </c><c> Yes    </c><c> [RFC4106][1] </c>
<c>ENCR_NULL_AUTH_AES_GMAC </c><c> MAY      </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC4543]  </c>
<c>Reserved for IEEE P1619 XTS-AES </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT  </c><c> No     </c><c> [Matt_Ball] Non IPsec</c>
<c>ENCR_CAMELLIA_CBC    </c><c> MAY      </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC5529] </c>
<c>ENCR_CAMELLIA_CTR    </c><c> MAY      </c><c> No     </c><c> [RFC5529] </c>
<c>ENCR_CAMELLIA_CCM_8  </c><c> MAY      </c><c> No     </c><c>[RFC5529]  </c>
<c>ENCR_CAMELLIA_CCM_12 </c><c> MAY      </c><c> No     </c><c>[RFC5529]  </c>
<c>ENCR_CAMELLIA_CCM_16 </c><c> MAY      </c><c> No     </c><c>[RFC5529]  </c>
<c>ENCR_CHACHA20_POLY1305 </c><c> SHOULD     </c><c> Yes    </c><c>[RFC7634]  </c>  
         
          <postamble>
          [1] - This requirement level is for 128-bit keys. 256-bit keys are at SHOULD.
          192-bit keys can safely be ignored.
          [IoT] - This requirement is for interoperability with IoT.           
            </postamble>
        </texttable>

         <t>IPsec sessions may have very long life time, and carry multiple packets, 
         so there is a need to move 256-bit keys in the long term. For that purpose 
         requirement level is for 128 bit keys and 256 bit keys are at SHOULD 
         (when applicable). In that sense 256 bit keys status has been raised from 
         MAY in RFC7321 to SHOULD.
         </t>   

         <t>IANA has allocated codes for cryptographic algorithms that have 
         not been specified 
	 by the IETF. Such algorithms are noted as UNSPECIFIED. Usually, 
         the use of theses algorithms
	 is limited to specific cases, and the absence of specification makes 
	 interoperability difficult for IPsec communications. These 
	 algorithms were not been mentioned in <xref target="RFC7321"/> and 
         this document clarify that such algorithms MUST NOT be implemented 
         for IPsec communications.</t>

	 <t>Similarly IANA also allocated code points for algorithms that are
	 not expected to be used to secure IPsec communications. Such algorithms
	 are noted as Non IPsec. As a result, these algorithms MUST NOT be implemented.</t>
	 
	 <t>ENCR_DES_IV64, ENCR_DES, ENCR_RC5, ENCR_IDEA, ENCR_CAST, ENCR_BLOWFISH 
         are obsolete algorithm that presents some weakness to differential cryptanalysis. 
	 DES was explicitly mentioned as MUST NOT in <xref target="RFC7321"/> as DES 
	 is known to be vulnerable. As result, its status remains MUST NOT. Other 
         algorithms were not mentioned in <xref target="RFC7321"/> and MUST NOT 
         be implemented. </t>

		 
	<t>ENCR_3DES status has been downgraded from  MAY in RFC7321 to SHOULD NOT. 
         However, ENCR_CHACHA20_POLY1305 seems a more modern approach alternative
         to AES than 3DES
         and so it expected to be favored over 3DES.</t>

	 <t>ENCR_NULL status was set to MUST in <xref target="RFC7321"/> and remains to MUST
	 to enable the use of ESP with only authentication. 
         It is expected to remain MUST by protocol requirements. In addition, 
         the use of ESP_NULL is preferred over AH due to NAT traversal.</t> 
        
	<t>ENCR_AES_CBC status remains to MUST. 
	ENCR_AES_CBC MUST be implemented in order to enable interoperability 
        between  implementation that followed RFC7321. However, there is a trend for
	the industry to move to AEAD encryption, and the overhead of ENCR_AES_CBC
	remains quite large so it is expected to be replaced by AEAD algorithms 
	in the long term.</t>
        
	<t>ENCR_AES_CTR status was set to MAY <xref target="RFC7321"/>, and 
	remains to MAY. ENCR_AES_CTR, does not present specific known 
	vulnerabilities. On the other hand,  it is not especially considered for 
	interoperability, and is not AEAD. As a result, it implementation remains
	optional.</t> 
		
	<t>ENCR_AES_CCM status was set to MAY in <xref target="RFC7321"/>. ENCR_AES_CCM 
	with 8 byte ICV status have been raised from MAY to SHOULD. This document 
        considers it SHOULD be implemented in order to be able to interact with Internet
        of Things devices. As this case is not a general use case for VPNs, its status is
        expected to remain to SHOULD. In addition, as ENCR_AES_CCM with 12 or 16 byte ICV 
	is not a general use case for VPNs, their status remains optional and MAY be 
	implemented.</t>
		 
	<t>ENCR_AES-GCM_16 status has been updated from SHOULD+ to MUST
	in order to favor the use of authenticated encryption and AEAD algorithms.
         The main motivation for adopting AES-GCM for ESP is performance 
         as well as key longevity - compared to AES-CBC for example. This resulted in 
         AES-GCM widely implemented for ESP. ENCR_AES_GCM_12 or ENCR_AES_GCM_8 are not
	 mentioned in <xref target="RFC7321"/>, and their status remains optional and MAY 
	 be implemented.</t>
         
	 <t>ENCR_NULL_AUTH_AES_GMAC was not mentioned in <xref target="RFC7321"/>. It 
	only provides authentication. As using IPsec for 
	non-encrypted traffic is not current practise, this algorithm remains optional 
	and MAY be implemented.</t> 
		 
	<t>ENCR_CAMELLIA* suite was not mentioned in <xref target="RFC7321"/>. 
	 ENCR_CAMELLIA* is not widely used. Its status remains optional and
         MAY be implemented.</t> 
		 
	<t> ENCR_CHACHA20_POLY1305 was not ready to be considered at the time of RFC7321.
        It has been recommended by the CRFG and others as an alternative to AES and AES-GCM. 
        It is also being standardized for IPsec for the same reasons. At the time of writing, 
        there were not enough ESP implementations of ENCR_CHACHA20_POLY1305 to be able to 
        introduce it at the SHOULD+ level. Its status has been set to SHOULD and is expected
        to become MUST in the long term.</t>
         
		  
        
		
<!--
<figure><artwork>
Requirement    Authenticated Encryption Algorithm
SHOULD+        AES-GCM with a 16 octet ICV [RFC4106]
MAY            AES-CCM [RFC4309]
</artwork></figure>

<figure><artwork>
Requirement    Encryption Algorithm
MUST           NULL [RFC2410] 
MUST           AES-CBC [RFC3602]
MAY            AES-CTR [RFC3686]
MAY            TripleDES-CBC [RFC2451]
MUST NOT       DES-CBC [RFC2405]
</artwork></figure>
-->

</section>

<section title="ESP and AH Authentication Algorithms">

<t>Encryption without authentication MUST NOT be used. As a result, authentication algorithm recommendations in this section are targeting two types of communications: Firstly authenticated only communications without encryption -- such communications can be ESP with NULL encryption or AH communications.  
Secondly, communications that are encrypted with non AEAD encryption algorithms mentioned above. In this case, they MUST be combined with an authentication algorithm.</t>

   
<texttable anchor="tbl_alg4" suppress-title="true">
          <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Status</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Comment</ttcol>
<c>AUTH_NONE                 </c><c> MUST / MUST&nbsp;NOT     </c><c> [RFC7296]  AEAD        </c>
<c>AUTH_HMAC_MD5_96  </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT </c><c> [RFC2403][RFC7296] </c>
<c>AUTH_HMAC_SHA1_96 </c><c> MUST-    </c><c> [RFC2404][RFC7296] </c>
<c>AUTH_DES_MAC       </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT </c><c> [UNSPECIFIED]      </c>
<c>AUTH_KPDK_MD5      </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT </c><c> [UNSPECIFIED]      </c>
<c>AUTH_AES_XCBC_96  </c><c> SHOULD   </c><c> [RFC3566][RFC7296] [IoT] </c>
<c>AUTH_HMAC_MD5_128 </c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT </c><c> [RFC4595] Non IPsec </c>
<c>AUTH_HMAC_SHA1_160</c><c> MUST&nbsp;NOT </c><c> [RFC4595] Non IPsec</c>
<c>AUTH_AES_CMAC_96  </c><c> MAY    </c><c> [RFC4494] </c>
<c>AUTH_AES_128_GMAC </c><c> MUST    </c><c> [RFC4543] </c>
<c>AUTH_AES_192_GMAC </c><c> MAY    </c><c> [RFC4543] </c>
<c>AUTH_AES_256_GMAC </c><c> SHOULD    </c><c> [RFC4543] </c>
<c>AUTH_HMAC_SHA2_256_128 </c><c> MUST   </c><c>[RFC4868]  </c>
<c>AUTH_HMAC_SHA2_384_192 </c><c> MAY    </c><c> [RFC4868] </c>
<c>AUTH_HMAC_SHA2_512_256 </c><c> SHOULD </c><c> [RFC4868] </c>


          <postamble> 
          [IoT] - This requirement is for interoperability with IoT 
            </postamble>
        </texttable>

        <t>AUTH_NONE has been downgraded from MAY in RFC7321 to MUST NOT. The only reason NULL 
        is acceptable is when authenticated encryption algorithms are selected from 
        <xref target="sec-encr"/>. In any other case, NULL MUST NOT be selected. As ESP and
        AH provides both authentication, one may be tempted to combine these protocol to 
        provide authentication. As mentioned by RFC7321, it is NOT RECOMMENDED to use 
        ESP with NULL authentication - with non authenticated encryption - in conjunction
        with AH; some configurations of this combination of services have been shown to be
        insecure <xref target="PD10"/>. In addition, ESP NULL authentication cannot be
        combined with ESP NULL encryption.</t>
        
	<t>AUTH_HMAC_MD5_96, AUTH_KPDK_MD5 were not mentioned in RFC7321.
	As MD5 is known to be vulnerable to collisions, it MUST NOT be used. </t>

        <t> AUTH_HMAC_SHA1_96 status has been downgraded from MUST in RFC7321 to MUST- as 
        there is an industry-wide trend to deprecate its usage.</t>
		
	<t>AUTH_DES_MAC was not mentioned in RFC7321. As DES is known to be vulnerable, 
	it MUST NOT be used.</t>
		
	<t>AUTH_AES_XCBC_96 is only recommended in the scope of IoT, as Internet of Things 
        deployments tend to prefer AES based HMAC functions in  order to avoid
        implementing SHA2. For the wide VPN deployment, as it has not been widely adopted,
        it has been downgraded from SHOULD in RFC4307 to MAY.</t>

        <t>AUTH_AES_CMAC_96 was not mentioned in RFC7321. It is not known to be vulnerable, 
	but it has not been widely been used. As a result, its implementation remains optional
	and it MAY be implemented. </t>

        <t>AUTH_AES_128_GMAC status is being upgraded from SHOULD+ to MUST in order to guarantee
        interoperability between implementation that are following RFC7321 and this document.
        In fact AUTH_HMAC_SHA1_96 was used to be the algorithm that provided interoperability
        and it has been downgraded.</t> 
		
	<t>AUTH_AES_192_GMAC was not mentioned in RFC7321. It is not widely used, and 
	AUTH_AES_256_GMAC would be preferred in case AUTH_AES_128_GMAC requires stronger 
	security. As a result it remains optional and MAY be implemented.</t>

	<t>AUTH_AES_256_GMAC was not mentioned in RFC7321. Its status has been set to SHOULD 
        as as a future replacement of AUTH_AES_128_GMAC or when stronger security is required.</t> 
	
        <t>AUTH_HMAC_SHA2_256_128 was not mentioned in RFC7321, as no SHA2 based authentication
        was mentioned. AUTH_HMAC_SHA2_256_128 SHOULD be implemented  in order to 
        replace AUTH_HMAC_SHA1_96.</t>

        <t>AUTH_HMAC_SHA2_512_256 SHOULD be implemented as a future replacement of 
        AUTH_HMAC_SHA2_256_128 or when stronger security is required. This value has been preferred
        to AUTH_HMAC_SHA2_384, as the overhead of AUTH_HMAC_SHA2_512 is negligible.</t>


        

    

       <!--
<figure><artwork>
Requirement    Authentication Algorithm (notes)
MUST           HMAC-SHA1-96 [RFC2404]
SHOULD+        AES-GMAC with AES-128 [RFC4543]
SHOULD         AES-XCBC-MAC-96 [RFC3566]
MAY            NULL [RFC4303]
</artwork></figure>

-->

</section>

<section title="ESP and AH Compression Algorithms">
<texttable anchor="tbl_alg3" suppress-title="true">
          <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Status</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Comment</ttcol>
          <c>IPCOMP_OUI</c><c>MUST&nbsp;NOT</c><c>UNSPECIFIED</c>
          <c>IPCOMP_DEFLATE</c><c>MAY</c><c>[RFC2393]</c>
          <c>IPCOMP_LZS</c><c>MAY</c><c>[RFC2395]</c>
          <c>IPCOMP_LZJH</c><c>MAY</c><c>[RFC3051]</c>
          <postamble> 
          [IoT] - This requirement is for interoperability with IoT 
            </postamble>
        </texttable>
        <t>Compression was not mentioned in RFC7321. As it is not widely used, 
        when specified, it remains  optional and MAY be implemented.</t>
</section>


<!--
<section title="Summary of Changes from RFC 4835">
<t>The following is a summary of the changes from RFC 4835.</t>
<figure><artwork>
Old            New
Requirement    Requirement      Algorithm (notes)
MAY            SHOULD+          AES-GCM with a 16 octet ICV [RFC4106]
MAY            SHOULD+          AES-GMAC with AES-128 [RFC4543]
MUST-          MAY              TripleDES-CBC [RFC2451]
SHOULD NOT     MUST NOT         DES-CBC [RFC2405]
SHOULD+        SHOULD           AES-XCBC-MAC-96 [RFC3566] 
SHOULD         MAY              AES-CTR [RFC3686]
</artwork></figure>
</section>
-->


<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>None.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">
  
&RFC2119;
&RFC4301;
&RFC4302;
&RFC4303;
&RFC7634;
&RFC7321;

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

&RFC2404;
&RFC2405;
&RFC2410;
&RFC2451;
&RFC3566;
&RFC3602;
&RFC3686;
&RFC4106;
&RFC4309;
&RFC4543;
&RFC4835;

<reference anchor="PD10">
<front>
<title>On the (in)security of IPsec in MAC-then-encrypt
configurations (ACM Conference on Computer and Communications
Security, ACM CCS)</title>
<author initials="K." surname="Paterson">
<organization>P</organization>
</author>
<author initials="J." surname="Degabriele">
<organization/>
</author>
<date year="2010"/>
</front>
</reference>




</references>

</back>
</rfc>
